All right, we're here.
Took us a little while, but we're here at Composition API,
and it's time to talk about the brand new thing that is with View3.
The first thing I want to caveat when it comes to the Composition API is that
even though it was introduced in View3,
there actually are ways to use it on View2.
So that is one of the things that the team has tried to work really hard on,
is that even though there are certain performance optimizations
and typescript enhancements that have come with View3,
as a whole, when it comes to feature parity,
the team has actually worked really hard to try to keep it as
basically cross-compatible as humanly possible,
because they know a lot of times people,
when they're working on enterprise apps,
as much as developers would love to be on the cutting edge tool,
the reality is that most of the time there's just no time to do that.
So rather than have developers be feeling left out of the fact that they might want
to rewrite their components using Composition API,
we basically have plugins that allow you to plug in
the Composition API into View2.
So again, while this is a View3 feature,
just know that you can use this in View2,
you just need to look into the plugin.
All right. So Composition API, let's talk about it.
So remember this life cycle diagram that we talked about earlier?
Up here, you'll notice in blue there's
a very special life cycle hook that's called Setup.
So Setup has a very special meaning for us in View because why?
Anytime you basically see the setup keyword,
the life cycle hook, you are basically
insured that you're using Composition API and think
that's one reason why the diagram here actually has it in parentheses.
It's because as we can see here,
prior to the setup function, there is nothing else.
So this is what's interesting about the Composition API is that it
happens before the options API.
So what does that really mean?
So we take a look at our code.
I'm going to hop into the playground so that we can just
kind of code some stuff without messing up say, love you,
go into the playground, and then we'll mpn run dev.
Boom.
We have a Pokedex app, and it's running.
All right.
So let's go ahead and see what is going on here.
Oh, for whatever reason, it did not open the actual folder.
There we go.
So close this, close this.
We're in playground right now.
If we take a look at our app.view,
you'll notice here that we're running a fetch,
and we're doing all this stuff inside of created.
Now, I mentioned that the setup function actually
happens before init.
So actually, if you think about asynchronous functions,
they really should be run in the setup function,
because that's its earliest point of starting
sort of like the component lifecycle.
So how that might look is that we actually
would have a setup function that's up here at the top.
And the reason I think it's important to organize your code
this way in putting setup at the top
is because everything else below it does not exist.
And it's useful to kind of think of it this way,
is that, ah, yes, this is what I'm doing inside of here.
Now, the thing that makes the Composition API particularly
unique when it comes to view is that everything inside of here
is truly vanilla JavaScript.
So in other words, there's so what we can't just go like,
oh, data, function, return, like Pokedex,
like all this stuff is gone.
Because why?
Composition API is about, let's say, I guess we'll
call it freedom and flexibility.
One of the advantages of Options API
is that it provides a very consistent way for you to add stuff.
Here's where my data goes, here's where my methods go,
here's where my computer properties go.
But over time, as people have scaled their applications
and components, there are times where people found
that they wanted to actually group things according
to their concerns and maybe find ways
to organize their codes in different ways.
And Composition API lets you do that.
But what that means, though, is that it's a free-for-all
in that you have to organize everything yourself.
So in the instance of setup, let's
have a reactive name variable in this case
for the region of Pokemon that this is tracking.
So the first thing is to remember,
this is vanilla JavaScript.
So we actually have to declare the variables manually now.
So const, let's see, region, name, it goes conto.
Great.
Now here's the thing, though.
When we actually look at this, let's
look inside the DevTools and look at our app.
We'll see here that nothing exists right now.
Only the Pokedex is showing up.
And the reason for that is because once you're
inside of setup, Vue is not doing any magic for you.
You have to actually start being very explicit about what's
happening.
So the thing about the Composition API
is that inside of here, Vue is not doing any magic for you.
So unlike when we're inside of data and methods
where you can just call the discontext
and it knows to, like, this that Pokedex
knows to go inside of data to go get the Pokedex,
like, inside of here, everything is like, OK,
you want to freedom, here's freedom.
And so what does that mean?
That means that at the end of setup,
we actually have to manually return anything
we want to expose.
And at first, that might sound a little bit redundant, right?
You're like, wait, why would I want to do that?
Well, because what you see now inside of DevTools
is that, check it out, the region name is appearing.
And the reason for that is because when you're writing
the JavaScript up here, you probably
don't want everything being exposed to your component.
There are times certain things might be, call it private.
And there are things where you're running calculations
that aren't relevant to the template
to the rest of the component.
And so that you can keep all up here.
And what you're doing here is then you're returning it.
And so when you return it, now it's actually
something that you can actually access.
So let's say inside of this created method,
now it can be, like, log this.regionname.
And so we'll see now inside of here, there you go.
The created lifecycle hook now has access to the data
that we set up inside of setup.
Didn't mean to do that, but that's how it worked out.
OK.
So the question here is, all right, well,
I want the ability to run an async function at this point.
And so your first instinct might be like, well, OK,
this makes sense.
What we're going to do here is we're
going to create a const of pokedex.
And we'll just copy over this await function.
And then we'll just make sure that setup is async.
Creates this as an await.
And then we'll return the pokedex here.
And let's keep that actually alphabetical.
And then you might, OK, and then since we're returning it
anyways, you don't need to define the data twice.
So there we go.
And then we actually don't even need this method anymore,
right, because we just refactored it.
And then, well, we're not even, we're
running this inside of here.
So actually, now that I think about it,
we could just say, we just need to delete this.
And then ideally, we could then just say this.pokedex.
So we should see the region name and the pokedex show up.
But you're going to see a view yelling at you
in a pretty big way.
And I wanted to show this error because most of the time,
this is not going to be something you run into.
But especially when you're getting started
and you see this error, it's probably
going to be a bit confusing, because you're
going to look at this.
And if we read it, it says that the setup function
returned a promise, but no suspense boundary has been defined.
And that's a lot of words, right?
You're like, what the heck is going on?
Well, so just to let you know, what is suspense?
So we look inside of the docs.
Suspense is another built-in component
that is experimental currently with view.
And the idea behind this is that it's
trying to help us better offload performance when
it comes to asynchronous options.
So in the sense of when you're loading something
asynchronously, you can have a fallback.
So the way that code works, as you can see here, is that do,
do, do, you can see here.
So you would load a, you would drop in your suspense component.
And you would say, OK, this is my dashboard
that I'm loading a bunch of async stuff happening.
But in case that fails, or frankly, it's not ready for me yet,
I'm going to go ahead and fall back to this template.
This intact should look familiar to you, because earlier,
we talked about slots.
And so here is that vslot fallback.
And this is already defined on the suspense component.
And so what you'll end up seeing on the page
is you'll see loading first.
And whenever it's ready, view will automatically
switch it over to the dashboard.
And so this is actually really useful.
But the key thing here, though, to understand,
though, especially at this point in the recording,
is that it is experimental.
So this is why at this moment, we're
not going to go into depth regarding how to use it
and that kind of thing.
Keep an eye on the docs if you want to play around with it.
But know that this will probably be
a pretty key part of a lot of framework approaches
going forward, as a lot of frameworks
are trying to figure out better ways of server-side rendering
different things and how to improve performance when
it comes to loading JavaScript on a page and so forth.
Now, when it comes to our error, though,
the reason this is a problem at this particular point in time
is because if we think about it from the tree itself,
the app.view is the root component of everything.
So you can't really suspend your root component
in a state of nothingness.
That doesn't work.
And so what you actually have to do that, in the case that you
really do need to do asynchronous operations
in Composition API, this is where you
need to put it into a component.
Because the app.view basically needs
to be in a stable state.
That's like, OK, I know where everything is.
And then this component over here is going to do some stuff.
I'm going to hang on to it and give it a backup.
And then I can do other stuff over here.
But if we suspend app.view, the whole thing basically,
like, because of how asynchronous operations work,
it just runs the risk of corrupting it.
So this is why we don't run async setup
at the root level at app.view.
So to show how this works, then, is
we're going to go ahead and create a component called
Pokedex.
And this is where we're going to go ahead
and then we'll have our script tag.
And we'll have our template.
If it would auto-complete, sometimes
Emmett is uncooperative with me.
OK, great.
So let's go ahead and blow this up into two columns.
So that's easier to follow.
We'll go ahead and bring over this asynchronous request
right here.
Actually, we can bring over the whole script block.
What am I talking about?
Bring over the whole thing, which is great.
And then this means that this script block is actually
no longer needed on this app.
Although, actually, we do need a script block
because why we need to actually import our Pokedex.
So Pokedex from components.pokedex.view.
And then we can register it on the components.
And then we have Pokedex like that.
You've got a case mix-up in the file name.
Do we have a case mix-up?
Oh, we do.
Did that again.
Thank you for catching that.
This is sometimes the trouble with the context switch.
OK, so inside of here, we'll have our template here
for the pre-fetch.
We don't even need this anymore, this button.
So all this is going to do is render that as a pre-block.
I mean, we can take this here, and then we
get the Pokedex like this.
OK, so let's take a look and see if this worked out the way
we wanted it to.
OK, so first thing first, we'll see
that when we're taking a look at this right now,
it's still yelling at us.
But we actually are seeing something rendered,
unlike before.
And it's because in this particular case, it's true.
We still need the actually suspense component at this point.
And so like I said, we're just going
to cover a high-level uses of it.
We're not going to dive deep into suspense as a component.
Because again, if we think about it from the view perspective,
is that view is saying, I don't know what to do with this yet.
So please give me some sort of fallback
so that in case this thing completely crashes,
we don't have this hanging component that's
not going to do anything.
So we bring in our suspense component,
and we say, OK, this is what I want you to render.
But in case things don't work, here's
the fallback where we'll say loading Pokedex data, just
like that.
Suspense, suspense, suspense, yep.
Yes, I already know that.
OK, so let's restart the server real quick just
to make sure that's not anything weird getting botched.
You don't have to import suspense?
No, import.
It's kind of like the global component.
It's just a global component that's registered.
Now, what's weird?
Oh, I forgot, yep.
OK, so inside of here, you're thinking, ah,
I did the suspense right, right?
I did it inside of my component because I gave it a fallback.
But this approach doesn't work because if we think about it
another way, it's happening at the child level.
And if we look at the error matches again,
it actually says that the suspense boundary needs
to be found at the parent tree.
Because if we think about it another way,
remember how we used to do the vif?
This is the same kind of concept where
you want the vif actually happening at the top
for something like suspense because it knows what to handle.
So if I go ahead and delete this stuff again,
this time we can actually say we'll have a suspense component
here that will then render out the Pokedex component
when it's ready, otherwise fall back to this text.
That's actually what's happening here.
And once we do that, there we go.
Now everything is working as expected.
And so again, the API for suspense is experimental.
But this mental model now of having the ability
to suspend your component and then have it switch out
with some sort of fallback is something
that is going to be more popular with Frameworks
and not just Vue.
And so something that I wanted you all to keep in mind
when it came to that.